In 1987, Tina Lord found herself in quite the pickle.
في عام 1987، تينا لورد وجدت نفسها في مأزق تماماً
See, this gold digger made sure she married sweet Cord Roberts
هذه المتيمة بالذهب حرصت أن تتزوج الجميل كورد روبرتس
just before he inherited millions.
قبل أن يرث الملايين
But when Cord found out Tina loved his money
ولكن عندما إكتشف كورد أن تينا تحب ماله
as much as she loved him,
بقدر حبها له،
he dumped her.
تخلى عنها
Cord's mother Maria was thrilled
والدة كورد ماريا شعرت بسعادة بالغة
until they hooked up again.
إلى أن إرتبطا مرة أخرى
So Maria hired Max Holden to romance Tina
لذا قامت ماريا بإستخدام ماكس هولدن كي يتودد لتينا
and then made sure Cord didn't find out Tina was pregnant with his baby.
ثم حرصت بأن كورد لا يكتشف أن تينا حامل بطفله
So Tina, still married but thinking Cord didn't love her
لذا تينا مازالت متزوجة ولكن تعتقد بأن كورد لم يكن يحبها
flew to Argentina with Max.
سافرت للأرجنتين مع ماكس
Cord finally figured out what was going on
كورد أخيرًا اكتشف بما يحدث
and rushed after them, but he was too late.
وأسرع إليهم، ولكنه كان متأخرًا جدًا
Tina had already been kidnapped,
حيث تينا قد اخُتطفت
strapped to a raft and sent over a waterfall.
ورُبطت بطوافة وأُرسلت عبر الشلال
She and her baby were presumed dead.
هي وطفلها يعتبران ميتان
Cord was sad for a bit,
كورد كان حزينًا قليلًا
but then he bounced right back
ولكنه نهض بعدها مرة أخرى
with a supersmart archaeologist named Kate,
مع عالمة آثار ذكية تدعى كيت
and they had a gorgeous wedding
وأقاموا حفل زفاف رائع
until Tina, seemingly back from the dead, ran into the church holding a baby.
حتى عادت تينا كما يبدو من الموت، وذهبت للكنيسة تحمل طفلًا صغيرًا
"Stop!" she screamed.
صارخةً " توقف! "
"Am I too late?
" هل أنا متأخرة جدًا؟
Cord, I've come so far.
كورد، لقد جئت الآن
This is your son."
وهذا ابنك "
And that, ladies and gentlemen,
وهذه أيها السيدات والسادة،
is how the soap opera "One Life to Live" introduced a love story
هي الطريقة التي قدم بها مسلسل " حياة واحدة نعيشها " قصة حب
that lasted 25 years.
استمرت لخمس وعشرين عامًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Now, if you've ever seen a soap opera,
والآن إن كنتم رأيتم مسلسل من قبل
you know the stories and the characters can be exaggerated, larger than life,
ستعلمون بأن القصص والشخصيات من الممكن أن تكون مبالغًا بها، أكثر من الحياة
and if you're a fan, you find that exaggeration fun,
وإن كنت من محبي المسلسلات، ستجد بأنها مبالغة ممتعة
and if you're not,
وإن لم تكن من محبيها
maybe you find them melodramatic or unsophisticated.
ربما تجدها ساذجة وبسيطة
Maybe you think watching soap operas
ربما تعتقد بأن مشاهدة هكذا مسلسلات
is a waste of time,
مضيعة للوقت،
that their bigness means their lessons are small or nonexistent.
وبأن ضخامتها تعني بأن دروسها صغيرة أو معدومة
But I believe the opposite to be true.
ولكن أنا أعتقد بأن العكس هو الصحيح
Soap operas reflect life, just bigger.
المسلسلات تعكس الحياة، فقط أكبر
So there are real life lessons we can learn from soap operas,
لذلك توجد دروس للحياة حقيقيه من الممكن أن نتعلمها من المسلسلات
and those lessons are as big and adventurous
وهذه الدروس كبيرة وتحتوي على المغامرات
as any soap opera storyline.
كأي قصة مسلسل
Now, I've been a fan since I ran home from the bus stop in second grade
الآن أنا اعتبر من المحبين حين هربت من المنزل في محطة الحافلات في الصف الثاني
desperate to catch the end of Luke and Laura's wedding,
فاقدة للأمل بأن أشاهد النهاية لحفل زفاف لوك ولورا،
the biggest moment in "General Hospital" history.
أكبر لحظة في تاريخ مسلسل " المستشفى العام "
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So you can imagine how much I loved my eight years
لذا لكم أن تتخيلوا كم كنت أحب سنواتي الثمان
as the assistant casting director on "As the World Turns."
كمساعدة مخرج في مسلسل " ويتحول العالم "
My job was watching soap operas,
كان عملي مشاهدة المسلسلات
reading soap opera scripts
قراءة نصوص المسلسلات
and auditioning actors to be on soap operas.
و إختبار الممثلين لمشاركتهم في المسلسلات
So I know my stuff.
حتى أعرف طاقمي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And yes, soap operas
وفعلاً، المسلسلات
are larger than life,
أكبر من الحياة،
drama on a grand scale,
دراما على نطاق واسع،
but our lives can be filled with as much intensity,
ولكن حياتنا بالإمكان ملأها بهكذا حدة
and the stakes can feel just as dramatic.
والركائز يمكن أن تحس بشكل مأساوي
We cycle through tragedy and joy
نحن في دورة حياة من المأساة والفرح
just like these characters.
تمامًا مثل هذه الشخصيات
We cross thresholds, fight demons and find salvation unexpectedly,
نحن نعبر العتبات، نقاتل الشياطين ونجد الإنقاذ بشكل غير متوقع
and we do it again and again and again,
ونفعل ذلك مرارًا وتكرارًا،
but just like soaps, we can flip the script,
ولكن مثل المسلسلات، بإمكاننا تغيير النص
which means we can learn from these characters
وهو ما يعني بأننا يمكن أن نتعلم من هذه الشخصيات
that move like bumblebees,
التي تتحرك مثل النحل،
looping and swerving through life.
تدور وتغير الإتجاه في هذه الحياة
And we can use those lessons
وبالإمكان الإستفادة من هذه الدروس
to craft our own life stories.
لصياغة قصص حياتنا الخاصة
Soap operas teach us to push away doubt
تعلمنا المسلسلات بأن ندفع الشك بعيدًا
and believe in our capacity
ونؤمن في قدراتنا
for bravery, vulnerability,
للشجاعة، الضعف
adaptability and resilience.
القدرة على التكيف، المرونة
And most importantly, they show us
والأكثر أهمية بأنها تظهر لنا
it's never too late to change your story.
بأن الأوان لن يفوت أبدًا لتغيير قصتك
So with that, let's start with soap opera lesson one:
لذا مع هذه الأمور دعونا نبدأ بالدرس الأول للمسلسلات:
surrender is not an option.
الاستسلام ليس خيار
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"All My Children"'s Erica Kane was daytime's version of Scarlett O'Hara,
شخصية ايريكا كين في مسلسل " كل أولادي " كانت النسخة اليومية لشخصية سكارليت اوهارا
a hyperbolically self-important princess
أميرة ذات أهمية ذاتية مبالغ بها
who deep down was scrappy and daring.
التي في أعماقها كانت غير مترابطة وجريئة
Now, in her 41 years on TV, perhaps Erica's most famous scene
الآن وفي عامها 41 في التلفزيون ربما يكون أشهر مشهد لإريكا
is her alone in the woods
هو عندما كانت لوحدها في الغابة
suddenly face to face with a grizzly bear.
وجهًا لوجه فجأةً مع دب رمادي اللون
She screamed at the bear,
صرخت على الدب،
"You may not do this!
" لا يمكنك القيام بذلك !
Do you understand me?
هل تفهمني؟
You may not come near me!
لا يمكنك الإقتراب مني !
I am Erica Kane
أنا إيريكا كين
and you are a filthy beast!"
وأنت وحش قذر ! "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And of course the bear left,
وبالطبع غادر الدب،
so what that teaches us
لذا ذلك يُعلمنا
is obstacles are to be expected
بأن العقبات يجب أن تكون متوقعه
and we can choose to surrender or we can stand and fight.
وثم بإمكاننا اختيار الاستسلام أو الوقوف والقتال
Pandora's Tim Westergren knows this better than most.
تيم ويستيرقرين مؤسس " باندورا " يعلم ذلك أفضل من الكثير
You might even call him the Erica Kane of Silicon Valley.
يُمكن أن تطلق عليه " إيريكا كين منطقة سيليكون فالي "
Tim and his cofounders launched the company
تيم وشُركاءه أطلقوا الشركة
with two million dollars in funding.
بتمويل 2 مليون دولار
They were out of cash the next year.
ولقد أفلسوا في العام التالي
Now, lots of companies fold at that point, but Tim chose to fight.
الكثير من الشركات تُغلق في تلك المرحلة، ولكن تيم اختار القتال
He maxed out 11 credit cards and racked up six figures in personal debt
بلغ الحد الأقصى لـ 11 بطاقة ائتمان وسدد ما يصل إلى ستة أرقام من الديون الشخصية
and it still wasn't enough.
ولا زال ذلك لم يكن كافيًا
So every two weeks for two years on payday he stood in front of his employees
لذلك كل أسبوعين لمدة سنتين في يوم دفع الرواتب كان يقف أمام موظفيه
and he asked them to sacrifice their salaries,
ويطلب منهم التضحية برواتبهم،
and it worked.
ولقد نجح
More than 50 people deferred two million dollars,
أكثر من 50 شخص أرجأ الاستلام وذلك وفر 2 مليون دولار
and now, more than a decade later,
والآن بعد مرور أكثر من عقد من الزمن،
Pandora is worth billions.
" باندورا " تُقدر بالمليارات
When you believe that there is a way
عندما تؤمن بأن هنالك طريق
around or through whatever is in front of you,
حول أو من خلال كل ما هو أمامك،
that surrender is not an option,
ذلك الاستسلام لن يكون خيارًا
you can overcome enormous obstacles.
يمكنك التغلب على عقبات هائلة
Which brings us to soap opera lesson two:
وهو ما يقودنا للدرس الثاني من المسلسلات:
sacrifice your ego and drop the superiority complex.
التضحية بذاتك وترك عقدة التفوق
Now, this is scary.
الآن هذا مخيف
It's an acknowledgment of need or fallibility.
هو اعتراف للحاجة أو العرضة للخطأ
Maybe it's even an admission
ربما حتى يكون القبول
that we're not as special as we might like to think.
بأننا لسنا متميزين كما نأمل
Stephanie Forrester of "The Bold and the Beautiful"
ستيفاني فوريستر شخصية مسلسل " الجريء والجميلة "
thought she was pretty darn special.
اعتقدت بأنها جميلة ومميزة
She thought she was so special,
اعتقدت بأنها مميزة جدًا
she didn't need to mix with the riffraff from the valley,
لم تكن بحاجة للاختلاط مع أراذل الناس من الوادي
and she made sure valley girl Brooke knew it.
وحرصت بأن فتاة الوادي بروك يعلم بذلك
But after nearly 25 years of epic fighting,
ولكن بعد ما يقرب 25 عام من القتال البطولي،
Stephanie got sick and let Brooke in.
ستيفاني مرضت وسمحت لبروك بالانضمام
They made amends,
قاموا بإصلاحات
archenemies became soul mates
ألد الأعداء أصبحوا أصدقاء الروح
and Stephanie died in Brooke's arms,
وستيفاتي ماتت بين أيدي بروك
and here's our takeaway.
وهذه استنتاجاتنا
Drop your ego.
اترك الأنانية
Life is not about you.
الحياة ليست عنك
It's about us,
الحياة عنا
and our ability to experience joy
وقدرتنا على تجربة السرور
and love and to improve our reality
والحب وتحسين واقعنا
comes only when we make ourselves vulnerable
تأتي فقط عندما نجعل أنفسنا عرضةً
and we accept responsibility for our actions
ونتقبل المسؤولية لأفعالنا
and our inactions,
وتراخينا
kind of like Howard Schultz, the CEO of Starbucks.
هكذا نوع مثل هاورد سكولتز المدير التنفيذي لستاربكس
Now, after a great run as CEO,
الآن وبعد مسيرة عظيمة كمدير تنفيذي
Howard stepped down in 2000,
هاورد ترك منصبه في عام 2000،
and Starbucks quickly overextended itself
وستاربكس توسعت بنفسها بسرعه
and stock prices fell.
وهبطت أسعار الأسهم
Howard rejoined the team in 2008,
انضم هاورد مرة أخرى للفريق عام 2008،
and one of the first things he did
و واحدة من الأمور الأولى التي فعلها
was apologize to all 180,000 employees.
كان الاعتذار لـ 180 ألف موظف جميعهم
He apologized.
هو اعتذر
And then he asked for help, honesty, and ideas in return.
ومن ثم طلب المساعدة، الصدق والأفكار بالمقابل
And now, Starbucks has more than doubled
والآن ستاربكس ضاعفت
its net revenue since Howard came back.
إيراداتها منذ انضمام هاورد مرة أخرى
So sacrifice your desire to be right or safe all the time.
لذا التضحية برغبتك من أجل أن تكون بحق أو أمان كل وقت
It's not helping anyone, least of all you.
هي ليست مساعدة أي شخص، على الأقل لك
Sacrifice your ego.
التضحية بأنانيتك
Soap opera lesson three:
الدرس الثالث للمسلسلات:
evolution is real.
النمو حقيقي
You're not meant to be static characters.
من غير المقصد بأن تكونوا شخصيات جامدة
On television, static equals boring and boring equals fired.
في التلفاز، الجمود يساوي الملل والملل يساوي الطرد
Characters are supposed to grow and change.
الشخصيات من المفترض أن تنمو وتتغير
Now, on TV, those dynamic changes
الآن على شاشة التلفاز، تلك التغييرات الديناميكية
can make for some rough transitions,
يمكن أن تُعمل لبعض التغيرات الصعبة
particularly when a character is played by one person yesterday
وخاصة عندما تُجسد شخصية من قبل شخص معين بالأمس
and played by someone new today.
وتُجسد من قبل شخص آخر اليوم
Recasting happens all the time on soaps.
تغيير الأدوار يحدث بكل وقت في المسلسلات
Over the last 20 years,
على مدى السنوات الـ 20 الماضية،
four different actors have played the same key role
جسد أربعة ممثلين مختلفين نفس الدور الرئيسي
of Carly Benson on "General Hospital."
لكارلي بينسون من مسلسل " المستشفى العام "
Each new face triggered a change in the character's life and personality.
كل وجه جديد أحدث تغيير في حياة الشخصية وشخصيتها
Now, there was always an essential nugget of Carly in there,
الآن توجد دائمًا حيوية في شخصية كارلي
but the character and the story adapted to whomever was playing her.
ولكن الشخصية والقصة تتكيف لأي ممثل يجسدها
And here's what that means for us.
وذلك ما يعنينا
While we may not swap faces in our own lives,
في حين أننا لا نتمكن من تبديل وجوهنا في حياتنا،
we can evolve too.
بإمكاننا التطور أيضًا
We can choose to draw a circle around our feet and stay in that spot,
بإمكاننا اختيار رسم دائرة حول أقدامنا والبقاء فيها،
or we can open ourselves to opportunities
ونستطيع فتح فرص لأنفسنا
like Carly, who went from nursing student to hotel owner,
مثل كارلي، الذي تحول من طالب تمريض إلى صاحب فندق،
or like Julia Child.
أو مثل جوليا جايلد
Julia was a World War II spy,
كانت جوليا جاسوسًا في الحرب العالمية الثانية
and when the war ended, she got married, moved to France,
وعندما انتهت الحرب، تزوجت وانتقلت إلى فرنسا،
and decided to give culinary school a shot.
وقررت التجربة في مدرسة للطهي
Julia, her books and her TV shows revolutionized the way America cooks.
جوليا وكتبها وبرامجها التلفزيونية أحدثت ثورة في طريقة الطبخ بأمريكا
We all have the power to initiate change in our lives,
جميعنا لدينا القوة في بدأ التغيير في حياتنا
to evolve and adapt.
في التطور والتكيف
We make the choice,
نحن لدينا الاختيار،
but sometimes life chooses for us, and we don't get a heads up.
ولكن أحيانًا الحياة هي من تختار لنا، ولا نحصل على فرصة الانتباه
Surprise slams us in the face.
المفاجأة تضربنا بقوة في وجوهنا
You're flat on the ground, the air is gone,
تكون مستلقي في الأرض، والهواء يتلاشى
and you need resuscitation.
وبحاجة للإنعاش
So thank goodness for soap opera lesson four:
لذا الشكر لله على الدرس الرابع من المسلسلات:
resurrection is possible.
الإنعاش متاح
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In 1983, "Days of Our Lives"' Stefano DiMera died of a stroke,
في عام 1983، في مسلسل " أيام من حياتنا " توفي ستيفانو ديميرا من سكتة الدماغية،
but not really, because in 1984
ولكن ليس حقًا، لأنه في عام 1984
he died when his car plunged into the harbor,
توفي عندما سقطت سيارته في الميناء،
and yet he was back in 1985 with a brain tumor.
ومع ذلك عاد في عام 1985 مع وجود ورم بالدماغ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But before the tumor could kill him,
ولكن قبل أن يقتله الورم،
Marlena shot him, and he tumbled off a catwalk to his death.
مارلينا أطلقت النار عليه، وقفز من المنصة لموته
And so it went for 30 years.
وهكذا استمر لمدة 30 عام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Even when we saw the body,
حتى عندما شاهدنا الجثة،
we knew better.
عرفنا بشكل أفضل
He's called the Phoenix for a reason.
أطلق عليه لقب فينكس لسبب ما
And here's what that means for us.
وهذا ما يعنينا
As long as the show is still on the air,
طالما أن العرض مازال على الهواء،
or you're still breathing,
أو أنك ما زلت تتنفس،
nothing is permanent.
لا شيء دائم
Resurrection is possible.
الإنعاش متاح
Now, of course, just like life,
الآن بالطبع، تمامًا مثل الحياة،
soap operas do ultimately meet the big finale.
المسلسلات في النهاية تلبي الخاتمة الكبرى
CBS canceled my show, "As The World Turns," in December 2009,
قناة CBS ألغت عرضي " ويتحول العالم " في ديسمبر 2009
and we shot our final episode
وأنهينا تصوير الحلقة الأخيرة
in June 2010.
في يونيو عام 2010
It was six months of dying
لقد كانت ستة أشهر من الموت
and I rode that train right into the mountain.
وركبت ذلك القطار المتجه إلى الجبل
And even though we were in the middle of a huge recession
وعلى الرغم من أننا كنا في وسط ركود كبير
and millions of people were struggling to find work,
والملايين من الناس تعاني في البحث عن عمل،
I somehow thought everything would be OK.
فكرت بطريقة أو بأخرى بأن كل شيء على مايرام
So I packed up the kids and the Brooklyn apartment,
لذلك حزمت أغراض الأطفال والشقة في بروكلين
and we moved in with my in-laws
وانتقلت إلى أقربائي
in Alabama.
في ألباما
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Three months later, nothing was OK.
وبعد ثلاثة شهور، لا شيء على ما يرام
That was when I watched the final episode air,
وكان ذلك عن شاهدت الحلقة الأخيرة على الهواء مباشرة،
and I realized the show was not the only fatality.
وأدركت بأن العرض ليس هو الفاجعة الوحيدة
I was one too.
أنا كنت كذلك أيضًا
I was unemployed and living on the second floor
أنا لم يكن لدي عمل وأعيش في الطابق الثاني
of my in-laws' home,
لمنزل أقربائي
and that's enough to make anyone feel dead inside.
وهذا يكفي لجعل أي شخص يشعر بالموت بداخله
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I knew my story wasn't over,
ولكني أدركت بأن قصتي لم تنتهي،
that it couldn't be over.
لا يمكن أن تنتهي
I just had to tap into everything I had ever learned about soap operas.
أود أن أستفيد من كل شيء تعلمته حول المسلسلات
I had to be brave like Erica and refuse to surrender,
كان عليّ أن أكون بشجاعة إيريكا وأرفض الإستسلام،
so every day, I made a decision to fight.
لذلك في كل يوم، أتخذ قرارًا بالقتال
I had to be vulnerable like Stephanie
كان عليّ أن أجعل نفسي عرضةً مثل ستيفاني
and sacrifice my ego.
وأضحي بأنانيتي
I had to ask for help a lot of times across many states.
اضطررت لطلب المساعدة في الكثير من الأحيان في العديد من الولايات
I had to be adaptable like Carly
كان عليّ أن أكون قابلة للتكيف مثل كارلي
and evolve my skills, my mindset, and my circumstances,
وأطور مهاراتي، عقليتي وظروفي،
and then I had to be resilient, like Stefano,
ومن ثم كان عليّ أن أكون مرنه مثل ستيفانو،
and resurrect myself and my career
وأحيي نفسي وحياتي المهنية
like a phoenix from the ashes.
مثل طائر العنقاء من الرماد
Eventually I got an interview.
في نهاية المطاف حصلت على مقابلة
After 15 years in news and entertainment,
بعد 15 عامًا في الأخبار والترفيه،
nine months of unemployment
تسعة شهور من غير عمل
and this one interview,
وهذه المقابلة الوظيفية،
I had an offer for an entry level job.
كان لدي عرضًا لوظيفة من مستوى مبتدئ
I was 37 years old
كنت أبلغ من العمر 37 عامًا
and I was back from the dead.
ولقد عدت من الموت
We will all experience what looks like an ending,
يتعين علينا جميعًا تجربة ما يشبه النهاية،
and we can choose to make it a beginning.
وباستطاعتنا الاختيار لجعلها كبداية
Kind of like Tina, who miraculously survived that waterfall,
مثل تينا التي نجت بأعجوبة من الشلال
and because I hate to leave a cliffhanger hanging,
ولأنني أكره ترك مسلسل المغامرات معلّق،
Tina and Cord did get divorced,
تينا وكورد تطلقا،
but they got remarried three times before the show went off the air in 2012.
ولكنهما تزوجا مرة أخرى ثلاث مرات قبل نهاية العرض عام 2012
So remember,
لذلك تذكروا،
as long as there is breath in your body,
طالما هنالك نفس في أجسامكم،
it's never too late to change your story.
لن يفت الأوان أبدًا لتغيير قصتك
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)